That was great. Praise the Lord.
For those of you that haven't met me, my name's Ryan. I'm a privilege of being one of the pastors here.
And I had an intentional stretch of four weeks off of preaching and then decided to get pneumonia.
So you all have not seen me in a while, which means I have a lot to say.
And yeah, it's going to be great. I'm out of time, but you know, there's also done with some ice cream.
So it's kind of balanced. Like, what do we do here?
This Sunday, we're celebrating for a lot of reasons.
And one reason is it's a year from our first Lord's trial service.
It's actually a year from the dead.
So if you all know how our teachers just came together, we decided to date each other for a couple of weeks before we signed the papers.
This is a year from our first date.
And God has done some incredibly amazing things to this community of believers.
We celebrated a couple of baptisms on Thursday.
We've been celebrating baptisms all year long.
It's been an incredible journey of God's faithfulness.
He's given tens of thousands of dollars away to missions, organizations, community outreach, partners.
God has been faithful and blessed.
And as incredible as it's been, it's daunting to me because there's so much more work to be done in this community for the kingdom of God.
And I'm just excited that we have decided to come together as a community to go after that bestness together for a long time.
And God's in charge of the fruit.
We don't have to make it happen.
So this Sunday is incredible.
We're finishing up this series that we've called We Are the Church.
It's our inaugural membership series.
It was also intended to go through our mission, vision, and values statement.
We got a little bit behind schedule on that, and so I have a really ambitious task this morning.
I'm going to do like a seven to ten minute TED Talk, reminding us of what that mission, vision, values, thing is, why we have it.
Then I'm going to pray and preach a sermon.
Okay?
So it's going to be, we're going to do our best.
And the reason I decided not to kind of split this into two weeks is because I really feel called and excited about this upcoming series on the book of John.
We've got about 15 weeks between now and Christmas, which is crazy to think about.
But the Gospel of John, we're going to be going through the seven I Am statements and seven miracles of Jesus in the Gospel of John.
And the book of John really is ready to convince the reader that Jesus is the Son of God.
And if Jesus is the Son of God, that changes literally everything.
And if he isn't, then why are we here?
Right?
And so what I would encourage you to do is this series is an excellent series to invite people to that don't know Jesus.
People that are spiritually curious that like the idea of Jesus but haven't given their lives to Jesus.
And so I'd love to encourage you to think about that.
Pray for those people in your lives.
But that's why I have way too much to be this morning.
So mission, vision, value, statements.
Why do organizations have it?
Why do we have it?
Is it really that necessary or important?
And how, who came up with them?
Who decided that this was a mission, vision, and value statement?
First, the process.
So at Canvas Community Church, we believe that my job as re-pastor is to test vision, but not to create vision.
That vision comes from us collectively.
Like what is God calling us as a church to do?
Not what is God calling me to do as a pastor.
I get to tell you what you have to do.
What is God calling us to do?
And so as we were putting together this mission, vision, and practice statement, I sat in the room with multiple people from both previous congregations for hours and hours.
Those of you that were there and looking for you, it was fun.
And so on day, I said, in an awesome process, we just prayed for discernment.
What is it that God has uniquely called our church to do?
Because the reality is there's a big C church and a little C church.
Big C church is all of us that have decided that Jesus is Lord and have submitted to his readership.
Like every human being on earth that has believed, placed, and faith, trusted Jesus is a part of the church.
And the church has a mission, vision, and values.
The mission is your great commission.
Go, make disciples, teach, baptize, right?
Like that's the mission of the church.
The vision of the church is to see the kingdom of God manifested on earth as it is in heaven.
The values that have found throughout the New Testament, right?
Like we as a big C church know what God's calling us to do.
But it's important then for each individual church to kind of define what is unique about us.
What makes us unique?
What is God calling us to specifically?
And so that's kind of why we have these statements.
And the purpose is that they help define who we are as a local church, what God is calling us to do.
And we developed it together as a group.
The board was involved in the process.
And so that's kind of how we got here.
C.S. Lewis also gives a really helpful illustration, I think, in New Christianity, where he says the whole idea of New Christianity is to define the lobby of Christianity.
Like the big C church, what is it that we all believe?
But then it's important that you move from the lobby into a room.
And the room is different unique churches, different theologies, different callings, different passions.
And so he gives this illustration of we're all in the same hall, but then we move from the hall into Christ's rooms.
And I kind of took that illustration and adapted it a little bit.
And I hope this makes sense.
I hope this helps for us.
It doesn't just forget that I've said it.
But so I kind of view the church, big C church, as we, a group of, as one of the vehicles moving north, powered by fossil fuels.
This is going to make sense in a second I've done this.
Right?
So the church is vehicles moving north, powered by fossil fuels.
That's the mission being in core practices of big C church.
But we as local churches, then you get to define what type of vehicle are we going to be.
Are we going to be an SUV?
Are we going to be a van?
Are we going to be a tent?
Probably not.
If you read the New Testament.
Are we going to be a boat?
Like what are we, what type of vehicle?
What color?
Like what style?
Or what form are we going to take on as a local church?
And then the vision is like, yeah, we're all moving north.
But what specific coordinates are we as a church headed towards?
Like what are we trying to tackle as a local church?
Like let's keep a specific coordinates in.
Not just north, but like which way north?
And then the practice is like, what type of fuel are we going to put into that vehicle that we've created?
Does that make sense?
So that's our mission, vision, and core practices.
So far we've talked about our core practices, not as explicitly as I would have liked to, because of all the problems that I told you we had.
So I'm going to re-match them for you.
Then I'm going to pray and preach a sermon that is going to unveil our mission and our vision statement.
Sound like a plan?
Awesome.
All right.
So here are the practices of chemistry and church.
This is the fuel, the thing that fuels our church uniquely to us.
We unite it to the faith of the gospel.
We prioritize primary theology.
Not that secondary theology isn't important, but we believe the gospel is too important for us to divide over things that don't matter.
Our church is good at this.
It's unique to us.
So I've been a part of so many conversations where people went into the room with this really important doctrine, something that they believed down to their thoughts was true.
And I heard them in the room say, I believe that this is true, but it's not so important that I'm going to divide over.
We're going to find unity for the faith of the gospel.
Secondly, we rely on the living and written word of God.
The Bible tells us what to do.
We don't get to redefine it for ourselves.
And the Bible points us to Jesus, who is the living word of God.
God incarnate in the flesh.
What he did, how he lived, should be prioritized in the way that we think and live.
Thirdly, we prioritize real relationships.
Some of the mornings are awesome.
Like a room full of people celebrating Jesus in his grave, but we want people to get out of rows and into circles.
To form genuine relationships where you know each other, what's going on, you know your kids' names, you know the difficulty that your families are going through, you're praying for one another, encouraging one another.
We want to prioritize real, authentic relationships.
And we want you to be okay with being honest with where you're at, not being fake, hiding, sinning.
Like we want to create a space where it's good for you to just come and say, this is who I'm in, this is where I'm at.
It's okay that you're there.
It's just not okay that you stay there.
Lastly, we cultivate our spiritual gifts to serve others.
The Holy Spirit was given to the church to empower us to do the things that God's calling us to do.
Each of us have a unique and special gift.
And if we put it on itself, if we allow the enemy to convince us not to use it, the whole church makes it done.
And so we want to cultivate your spiritual gifts, not for just the edification of the church, although it does that, but also to serve outside of these walls.
So, those are our practices.
That's the fuel that goes into what we do here as a church.
Let me pray, and then I'll pray to serving that will give us a misindexing at the end.
Father, thank you so much for this opportunity that we have to just talk about what is unique to us in the church, what you're calling us to in the surrounding community, the things that you want us to value.
God, may you create a fire in our souls for these things, that we be passionate about doing these things together.
And if these things don't resonate with us, God, may we have conversations about why.
And if it's not for us, may we find a church that's doing the thing that we feel called to do.
God, because the church is so much better when we're doing what God's calling us to do together as others.
So, lead us, God, as Jesus, wisdom, Holy Spirit, be chosen.
In the name of God, amen.
God's Bible, Jeremiah chapter 29 is where we're going to be.
I will get there in a few minutes, but if you want to put that on your phone, or it should be on the screen as well.
When I was first being Marissa, started to go visit with Sam and Lee, thinking that I was going to want to marry this girl.
And so, you know, you're forming this relationship with Sarah Karen, so you're, like, trying to, like, you know, figure stuff out and build that relationship.
Her dad was very clear that I was going to have to ask him for permission to marry her, which I love, but also, like, have some bridge building to do with her father, right?
So, in that process, I found out very quickly that her family are Philadelphia Eagle fans.
Yeah, and not only that, but they're, like, Philadelphia Eagle fans, right?
And if you're not familiar with football or football culture, the Eagles fans are, like, a different breed of fan.
Philadelphia is, like, a different breed of thingy.
And so, like, when they say they're fans, they're, like, really fans.
And I grew up around here, and so I was a Washington football fan.
And if you don't know football culture, Washington and Philly are rivals.
They are opposed to one another in all things.
And so I'm entering this relationship with this family that I'm trying to build bridges with.
And, like, life, this is going to be a lifelong thing, I'm hoping you're thinking, right?
And so I have a few options in this moment.
As I am a Washington fan and an Eagles fan, I can double dance, right?
I can fight this guy.
Like, yeah, you're a Eagles fan, I'm a Washington fan, and let's, like, rival, let's do this thing, right?
I can, like, double down on my fandom of the Washington football team and fight back, and we could just have this rivalry.
Maybe it's fun and playful, or maybe he makes me tell me I can't even get his daughter, right?
Like, there's possibilities there.
I can, like, withdraw and kind of pretend like I'm really not much of a football fan.
And I'm like, oh, my dad likes Washington, I don't know your kid.
You know, like, I can, like, I can downplay it, kind of come back from it.
Or I can just not tell him and pretend like I'm an Eagles fan and, like, you know, like, conform to his passing and we could be best friends.
And then he was definitely going to let me know his daughter, right?
So I've got a couple of options.
And I share this story with you because I wonder if you've ever found yourself in a similar social dilemma where there was going to be some relational things and you had a couple of options.
You could double down, you could fight, you could kind of shrink back three away, or you could conform to whatever it is that that person is passionate about.
And football teams are a bit of a trivial example of this.
But far more often these things happen with really important issues, really important ideas.
And I believe individual Christians and the church in America in an increasingly post-Christian culture, which, this is a sidebar, I don't think is a bad thing.
The church actually grows far more quickly and far more healthy when they're not in a position of power or authority.
And so as that culture gets increasingly post-Christian, we're put in these opportunities where we're building bridges and people outside of the church.
And I don't know about you, but sometimes it feels like I only have three options.
Sometimes it feels like I can fight back against this culture.
I can have a culture war against these ideas that are opposed to the things of God.
Like, our culture is proposing these ideas that are opposed to the things of God.
We think we rely on the written and living word of God, and then we go outside of these walls, and the culture is championing ideas that aren't in here.
So do I fight back?
Do I war against the people of the culture?
Do I shrink back into holy huddles with other Christians that think like me, talk like me, ask like me, believe like me, and we'll just pretend like nothing's happening outside of these walls?
Do I conform?
Do I, like, just take on the accidents of the culture around me?
I don't know about you, but oftentimes it feels like these are options, and none of them feel really good for me.
And so the reason we're turning to Jeremiah in chapter 29 this morning is because I believe Jeremiah 29 gives us a blueprint for a better option.
A better option for followers of God and a culture that is opposed to the things of God.
How do we navigate that system?
How do we build bridges and relationships with the culture that is opposed to the things of God?
Jeremiah 29 is just in context for those of you that don't know the Bible or don't know the Old Testament or whatever reason you don't know what's going on in Jeremiah 29.
You have a good reason to not know.
But Jeremiah is a prophet around the 6th century B.C., and he was writing to a group of Jewish hostiles who had been taken from their homeland and been brought into captivity in Babylon.
Babylon is a culture that is opposed to the things of God.
They've come in.
They've brought judgment.
And God, it has to tell us that God, like, uses them to bring judgment on the Israelites.
And so we've got God's people trapped in a godless nation.
And then Jeremiah writes them a letter of how they're supposed to live in this situation, in this situation that they find themselves in.
I wonder what you might be thinking.
What does a letter from 2,500 years ago to Jews in Babylon have anything to do with my life today?
Right?
Anybody?
Anybody think of that?
Well, I've made this joke many times, but I'm going to do it again for that for the moment.
I love when you ask the question of my not-long answer.
Let me get there.
And let me start with this quote from my friend, Josh Carlson, who says,
The Bible isn't just about what happens, but it's about what always happens.
And so, yes, this is a letter from 4,500 years ago, from a prophet to Jews set in Babylon.
But it's also about how probably people living in a secular culture can navigate these relationships.
See, throughout Scripture, Babylon, yes, Babylon is in real place.
This happened.
This is historical.
We could back it up about theology and history.
This happened.
But, throughout Scripture, Babylon isn't just a physical place, but it's symbolic for, it's a picture of any kingdom that sets itself up against the kingdom of God, that counterfeits the things of God.
So, yes, Babylon is a real place, but it also is this biblical concept of secular cultures that sets themselves up against the things of God.
Not only is Babylon a symbol for secular cultures, but exiles in Scripture has become a way that most often God's people exist.
Like, just retrace the history of the nation of Israel.
Like, oftentimes they find themselves as an exile.
Look at the history of the church.
Oftentimes, followers of God find themselves powerless and overseen by secular governments and cultures.
And so, yes, Jeremiah is writing two specific exiles in Babylon, but I think we can draw out some principles and options.
We find ourselves in 2023 in America, a close, increasingly post-Christian culture.
How do we navigate these questions?
And can I say, again, I think I said this a little bit earlier.
You hear the word exile, and you're like, I don't want a reference, right?
Right?
And I think this is why the church previously, and the generation before, worked really hard to, like, gain political power,
because nobody wants to be powerless.
We want influence.
We want power.
But look at the history of the church, and it grows most when it seemingly has no influence with power.
A group of exiles written according to the principles of God and in the cultures that sets itself up against the things of God
is one of the things that God uses most to build this church.
So, this is what Jeremiah writes to exiles in Babylon, but I think we can essentially say this is what God would say to us
to find ourselves as exiles in a post-Christian culture in America in 2023.
Jeremiah says, 21, 21, this one.
These are the words of the letter that Jeremiah and the prophets sent from Jerusalem to the surviving elders of the exiles
and to the priests, the prophets, and all the people who Meditizer had taken into exile from Jerusalem to Babylon.
Verse 4.
Jeremiah says,
Thus says the Lord.
This is what the Lord says to you as you are an exile in a nation that literally hates all of the things that you believe to be true.
Then says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, to all the exiles whom I have sent into exile from Jerusalem.
So, notice this wasn't necessary.
God allowed this to happen.
Build houses and live in them.
Plant gardens and eat their produce.
Take wives and have your sons and daughters.
Take wives to your sons and give your daughters a marriage that they need their sons and daughters and multiply there.
And do not eat trees.
So, up to this point, the exiles would have been like, yeah, that's what we do.
Like, that's what Israel has always done.
Israel has always, like, formed this community of other Jewish people.
They've kept to their identity.
And then they just trust God with the rest.
And empires fall.
And whatever happens, they're a tight-knit group.
And so, they would have been tracking with this.
But then, verse 7, but, fight back against the culture of Babylon and the people of Babylon.
Say that.
Say, seek the welfare of the city where I have sent you into exile and pray to the Lord on its behalf for its welfare.
For in its welfare, you will find welfare.
Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, do not let your prophets and your visitors who are among you deceive you.
And do not listen to the dreams that they dream.
For it is a lie that are prophesying to you in my name.
I did not send them to close the Lord.
So, in a situation where it seems like Israel might only have three options,
it seems like Jeremiah is giving them a foresight.
Right?
It feels like maybe fighting back against this culture of godless people might be our option.
We get together with strong, powerful, influential people,
and then we can form groups that have power and influence, and we can fight back.
Or maybe we just withdraw and create these holy huddles,
where we don't interact with people at all outside of these walls,
or maybe we just conform, we just become Babylonian,
and we'll be safe, and everything will be good, and we'll be comfortable, and life will be great.
Jeremiah seems to say,
those aren't a good option.
Those are better option.
He seems to say,
don't fight back against the culture.
Because when we fight back against the culture, we lose sight of who the real enemy is.
I've seen this play out so often in the church in America.
When the church fights back against the culture,
it makes the people of the culture respond.
We make the very people that Jesus Christ died for the enemy of the church.
We fight back not against the ideas, but against the people.
And Jeremiah is saying, don't fight back against the people.
Remember who the true enemy is.
Ephesians chapter 6 offers this.
We don't wrestle against flesh and blood, but against spiritual forces.
The great enemy of God is the one who is counterfeiting the kingdom of God's real secular culture.
Our enemy is not the people of the culture.
And so fighting is not an option.
Creating culture wars is not an option.
When we get confrontational with the people of Babylon,
we make the very people Jesus died for our enemies.
I love how Rich Valotus says it.
He says, it's a really curious evangelism strategy
to despise the people you're trying to bring to Jesus.
It's a really curious evangelism strategy to despise the people you're trying to bring to Jesus.
And here's the thing.
I don't believe, I know brothers and sisters in Christ
who's kind of taken and fighting back against the culture of its perspective.
And I don't believe that this is what their intention is.
I think slowly over time, that's how our culture interprets it.
They say, these people hate us.
They want nothing to do with us.
They don't listen to us.
They don't talk with us.
They just rally against the things that we value.
And so, when we fight back against the culture,
we make the wrong enemy the enemy.
So, Jeremiah said, don't fight back against the culture.
But he's also saying, don't withdraw from the culture.
They don't just do the Jewish thing and do really good Jews in Babylon
and ignore everything that's going on there.
He says, work for the prosperity of the culture.
Pray for the people of the culture.
And again, I think out of fear and irreverence for holiness,
sometimes we withdraw so much from the culture
because we don't want to conform to the totems of this world.
And so, we create these holy huddles of people that think like us,
talk like us, believe like us, act like us.
And when we withdraw from secular culture,
we give up valuable kingdom influence.
We're making opportunities to demonstrate the thought and life
of Jesus and the culture around them.
Jesus demonstrated for us how to treat idolatrous people
in a secular culture opposed to God's values.
He came to a people that despised him.
The God that created the universe came to earth.
And the people around set him up as their enemy
and he lovingly engaged in a relationship.
So much so that he literally laid down his life for them
to the point that when they were killing him
and mocking him, he looked to the Father
and he said, forgive them.
They're not my enemy.
They don't know what they're doing.
There's been tricked by a concrete culture.
The enemy of God has convinced them that I am their enemy
when really I am their savior.
So, don't put it against them.
Forgive them.
So, they don't know what they're doing.
And I think many of us, including myself,
become hard-hearted for the people of culture
or even as our enemies.
Others of us have become so afraid of cultural influences over us
that we've withdrawn, which, yet again,
in just another way, makes them our enemies.
But what if we fought back against both of these perspectives
by intentionally praying for the welfare of the people around us?
Imagine how God might send our hearts
towards people and culture
if we just praise them.
We just engage them in a relationship
when out of our way to intentionally connect.
So, not only is fighting or fleeing
not an appropriate response,
but neither is informing.
And this is, for me,
I'm just going to be as vulnerable
and friendly friend as possible.
This is the one that's most tempting for me
because I love people, right?
I want to have a good friendship
with every single one of you in this room,
which is not possible.
But I want it.
Like, I desperately want it.
And so,
I think many Christians,
we read passages like this from Jeremiah,
and we desperately want to love the people of our culture.
We don't want to be competitive or withdrawn,
but what we do instead
is slowly over time
and we just conform to the cultural values.
That's our counterfeit
to the values of the kingdom of God.
And then it's slowly over time
and we make one compromise
and another and another,
and before we know it,
there's nothing distinct about us
as Christ followers
from anyone else who doesn't follow Jesus.
And what God is not calling the Jewish upsellers to do
is to conform to Babylonian culture.
He wants them to flourish in Babylon
distinctly as Jews
while they work for the placing
of the Babylonian culture.
So,
it's not our job
to hold non-Christians
accountable to the standards
of the kingdom of God.
They don't agree with those ideas.
But it's also not our job
to pretend like they're not valuable to us,
like they're not important to us.
We don't apologize
or shrink up
from living distantly
in light of the kingdom of God.
We distinctly follow Jesus
in any culture
that is opposed to the things of Jesus.
And we do so lovingly
with compassion and intentionality
in prayer.
Jesus says this
in Matthew chapter 5.
For the temptation to conform.
He says,
You are the salt of the earth.
But salt loses its saltiness.
How can it be made salt to you again?
It is no longer good for anything.
He says,
If you lose your distinctness,
if you stop being distinctly a follower of Jesus,
then you won't be an influence
on the culture around you.
You will be useless
to the culture around you.
You are the light of the world,
a town built on a hill
that cannot be hidden either.
And people light a lamp
and put it under a bulb.
Instead,
they put it on a stand
and they give light
to everyone in the house.
In the same way,
let your light shine before others
that they may see
your good deeds
and glorify your Father in all.
This is Jesus saying
what Jeremiah was saying
to the apostles and Babylon.
Be distinctly Christian
to the culture around you.
Don't shrink back
from obeying the things of Jesus,
but do so in a way
that adds value
and love and compassion
to the culture around you.
Dr. Tony Evans says it this way.
He says,
God's people have been called
to penetrate society
as both salt and light.
I love that word,
penetrate.
He calls it
intentionally go into society
with salt and light.
Christians must offer others hope
because no earthly institution
can offer real hope
to this world.
Notice it says
you can't offer real hope.
The enemy counterfeits, right?
The enemy gives the culture
this false hope
and this false idea
that that'll last
when things are going good.
But when things go bad
for people who don't have
a hope beyond this life,
it's not a real hope at all.
And so we are called
to penetrate society
with that eternal hope
that comes through
Jesus' life
as a real life.
When we choose
to conform,
we're missing an opportunity
to shine in the light
of the humans
that are not into a world
that is just a great sport.
So,
fighting,
fleeing,
performing,
all not options.
What do we do?
Again,
I'm going to,
this is two Tim Matthew quotes
and one sermon.
Some of you are going to give me
a bunch of quotes for that
and some of you
are going to send me on that.
We're going to love
about our church
and be united
for the sake of the gospel.
Tim Matthew calls it
loyal subversion.
We're called to form
Christ-centered communities
with other followers
of Jesus
intentionally loving
the closer ones,
praying for its prosperity.
And I don't have time.
I wish I had time
to give you
the whole story
of Jeremiah.
But what happens
is the book of Daniel.
So,
if you're bored this week,
read Daniel chapter 1 through 9
and you will see
a small group
of Jewish exiles
in Babylon
doing the exact thing
that Jeremiah told them to do.
And you will see them
literally have
an incredible impact
on the Babylonian culture.
I wish I had time
to get to it.
There's example after example
of Daniel and his friends
exiles in Babylon
just navigating
this whole cultural
attention
so well.
Royally,
being loyal,
I don't know
how to turn that word
into the
storm I needed
to be in,
but you get it.
So,
check that out.
Daniel,
awesome.
A few principles
though that I think
I could draw out
from Daniel
without turning this.
Number one,
I would say
is build a balanced
community.
Work hard
to create a community
of other Christ followers
who speak
Jesus together.
Cultivate Godly
marriages,
families,
and friendships
with Jeremiah
and hotels
with their exiles.
Have healthy,
Godly marriages
and families.
Build a kingdom,
build a culture
of people
that the Babylonians
look at you,
the Babylonians
look at you
and they're like,
what's going on
with this weird
group of exiles
that we brought here
to be our slaves
and yet now
they're flourishing?
Why are they so happy?
Why are they so successful?
Create a culture
of a community
of believers
who speak
and Jesus together.
But it's a balanced
community.
This means we don't
isolate from the people
of the culture.
We build relationships
with them as well
intentionally looking
for friendships
with people
who hate the things
of God.
Intentionally
building friendships
with people
who hate the things
of God.
Yeah, right?
It's not easy
and it's not even
fun sometimes.
But think about
Jesus on the cross
being murdered
by Roman soldiers
who are gambling
for his clothes
and he says,
forgive them
for they don't know
what they do.
That's the perspective
we have
of people
outside the streets.
Not how dare they
shine and teach our kids
about so-and-so
or such and such.
We live once.
And we don't teach
our kids
so-and-so
and such-and-such
to conform to the culture.
We teach our kids
the values of God.
But we don't say
how dare they
shine and teach our kids
so-and-so
and such-and-such.
We stand for that
very person
Jesus Christ.
Create a balanced community.
Foster a spiritual burden
for the culture of the enemy.
This doesn't happen
after the night
or overnight.
We have to tell
these people.
And we have to
work hard
to build friendships
with them
slowly over time.
There's a book
by Rosario Butterfield
called
The Gospel Comes
with a House Key.
It's an incredible
testimony
that's happening.
She was a
lesbian English professor
at Syracuse University
in the 90s.
And like
this one
Christian family
infiltrated her life.
No questions asked.
Not asking her
to do anything
for them.
Just loving her
and slowly
over time
to expose
the gospel of Jesus.
Her life
is transformed
forever
and now
her life
is based on
inviting other people
into the home
going.
This is a
spiritual burden
for the culture
outside the church.
Let's do that.
So that
we can demonstrate
and then
declare
the kingdom
of God
to them.
Third,
remain faithful
to God
even when
it gets bad.
I'm going to read
a little bit more
of Jeremiah.
This is the verse
you guys really
just put on
coffee mugs
but without
contrast.
For thus
does the Lord
when 70 years
are completed
for Babylon.
Do we know
what he's saying
here?
You're going
to be brave
to a culture
that hates you
for 70 years.
I'm asking you
to be faithful
to me in the midst
of this really
difficult thing.
It's been far
too often
and I think
that this is why
culture wars
are so prevalent
in the American church
because we've been
discipled to believe
that we live
in a Christian nation
and so we should
have these services
and powers
and everything
should go well
for us
and life should
be awesome
because we followed
Jesus and you
should pass on
the best that I know
far more often
than not.
Followers of God
are actually
pushed to the margins.
This is what's
happening in Israel.
God says,
I'm going to let you
be in exile
for 70 years
for I know
the plans
I have for you
says the Lord
plans for welfare
and not for evil
to give you
a future
and a hope
in the midst
of the most
difficult time
of your life
claim to this
truth
I have a plan
for the future
of hope
for the future.
After 70 years
of exile
you will call
upon me
and come
and pray to me
and I will hear you.
You will seek me
and you will find me
when you seek me
with all of your heart.
I will be found
by you
declares the Lord
and I will restore
your fortunes
and gather you
from all of the nations
and places
where you have been
driven declares the Lord.
I will bring you
back to a place
from which I sent you
into exile.
This is the Old Testament
version of the Gospel.
Not everything
is going to be perfect.
is going to go well
for you.
But because
of the life
death, burial
and resurrection
of Jesus
I will be faithful
to my promises
there is a hope
for the future.
Jesus wins
in me
and the kingdoms
come and go
but Jesus
sits on the throne.
So no matter
what happens
here and now
over the next
50 to 100 years
in America
Jesus is King.
And so we cling
to that hope.
no matter how hard
it's in your spirit
we remain faithful
to God.
In case you guys
have plans for us
that's the beautiful
thing about the verse.
Without context
but it's true.
All of God's promises
find that yes
and amen
and Jesus
rulers,
empires,
and secular cultures
will come and go
but Jesus remains
on the throne
and will return
one day
to establish
his ruling.
I want to summarize
this whole message
in one statement
I would say
this Christian
asyls in secular culture
are called to live
for the prosperity
of the culture
without conforming
to its patterns
of fighting
against people.
So,
what does this
have anything
to do with our
mission and vision
statement?
This is the general
principle
I think
that our mission
and vision statements
come out of.
And that group
of people
that I told you
about at the beginning
of the message
we do that
as done this
to come up
with concise
language that
communicates
the type of vehicle
we want to be
and the direction
north we want
to head
as it takes.
But,
anybody that has
a Twitter account
knows that
when you take
really powerful
clues
and consolidate
them
you could
poke a hole
in it
probably,
right?
Right.
So,
let's not do that
because we unite
from the sacred
gospel.
Right.
So,
our mission
is to invite
real people
with real lives
into a Christ-centered
community.
We want to
cultivate
a community
of followers
of Jesus
that keep
seriously
following Jesus
together
and we want
to welcome
people into
them
to claim
the gospel
of Jesus
and that
develop
relationships
with people
who hate
the things
of God.
We want
to be
a God
of a community
in the mix
of a secular
culture.
And the real
people realize
things like
we want
to be real
with people.
We're not
perfect.
related to
believers,
right?
Like,
far too often
that's how we
want to project
ourselves
the people
that don't
value the
things that
God.
If we want
to be real,
like,
we want
to be good
at this thing
and we're
not.
And so let's
just be honest
with the people
that we're
trying to build
relationships with.
Cultivating a few
people who are
living in God's
kingdom values
on earth,
not withdrawing
from others,
but inviting
them to come
and see God's
hope for the
world in a
relevant and
accessible way.
Our vision,
the specific
direction north
that we
are having.
We want
to cultivate
the kingdom
of God
by proclaiming
Jesus clearly
and obeying
Jesus boldly.
God is going
to build
his kingdom.
We just
want to be
a part of
it.
How are we
a part of
it?
By proclaiming
Jesus,
his life,
death,
burial,
resurrection,
his love,
compassion,
unconditional
forgiveness,
and obeying
him boldly.
May we not
be a church
since here's
the message
of Jesus
about delivering
the life
that you
live.
Let's do
both and
together.
So success
for us,
it's important
that I point
this out
with our
vision,
is that
success for
us isn't
about more
attendance
or successful
ministries,
but it's
about seeing
God's kingdom
exponents
and faithful
obedience
for God's
purpose.
If our
church never
grows another
person but
the kingdom
of God
in our city
grows,
we win.
new
women.
That doesn't
mean I
don't want
to reach
more people
and make
more room.
Let's do
that.
But if we
don't ever
accomplish
that,
that the
kingdom of
God is
cultivated
outside of
our city,
people in
the church
club,
Jesus,
and hope,
and hearing,
and hence,
we win.
So,
I don't know
about you,
but it gets
me pumped.
Imagine what
God might
do with a
group of
faithful followers
that Jesus
committed
sacrificially
works for
the prosperity
of the
culture around
us without
conforming to
his practices
of fighting
against his
people.
Imagine how
the five
blocks
surrounding
this building
might be
different if
we do this
faithfully over
the long term.
Imagine what
your families,
your villages,
your workplaces,
your neighborhoods
could look like
if we all took
this blueprint
seriously,
and the values
of the kingdom
of God
became visible
to raise
around us.
What if we
became a
tithing oasis
to a people's
first and
third relationship
with God
and all of
them?
We think
he's created
this pocket
of rice-giving
water in a
desert of
general land.
So,
follow our
views of this.
I'd like you
to consider
what ways
you have
been tempted
to default
to fighting
against culture,
withdrawing from
culture,
or conforming
too closely.
Consider that
this week.
Think about
that.
Honestly,
take an
evaluation
of your
life.
How might
God be
asking you
to reform
the way
you go
about relating
to secular
culture?
If you're
in here
and you
don't know
Jesus,
I'd like you
to consider
the possibility
that you've
been given
to this whole
time by
many of
God
who's
trying to
just distress
you wrong
enough
for you to
just live
a life on
and miss
out on
the things
that God
has to,
consider the
possibility
that God's
kingdom might
actually be
a better
way to
live,
a hope
and a future
beyond this
way.
There's another
prophet around
the same time
as Jeremiah
and Isaiah
and he wrote
this to people
outside of the
kingdom of God
about the
kingdom of God.
So if you're
here and you're
like, hey,
I don't think
I'm eating
on my
world
this yet,
this is what
I would say
to you.
This idea
of those
outside the
kingdom
is come,
all you
who are
thirsty,
come to
the waters.
You who
have no
money,
come buy
and eat.
Come buy
wine and milk
without money
and without
cost.
Why spend
money on
what is not
bread?
You've been
sick.
This is the
real thing.
And you
labor on
what does
not satisfy
them.
Listen to
me and eat
what is good
and you will
delight in the
riches of the
poor.
Give ear and
come to you.
Listen that
you may live.
I will
make an
everlasting
covenant with
you.
My faithful
will have
promised the
day to
seek the
Lord while
he may be
found.
Call on
him while
he is
near.
Let the
wicked forsake
their ways
and the
annihilates
their lives.
Let them
turn to the
Lord and
he will
have
mercy on
them.
And to
our God
he will
freely
pardon you.
He says
this,
my thoughts
are not
your thoughts
neither are
my ways
your ways
to praise
the Lord.
As the
heavens are
higher than
the earth
so are
my ways
higher than
your ways
and my
thoughts
higher than
your time.
This means
God's
kingdom.
Since
Catholic
spring
gives
fathers
to the
orphan
families
to the
spring
years
provides
food for
those
who need
forgiveness
for those
who are
above
and living
water that
never runs
away.
May we be a
people that live
according to these
values,
the glory of God
and the good of our
neighbor.
We would create a
question of community
inviting others to
come along.
May we see the
kingdom of God
cultivated on earth
as it is in heaven
and be safe
for your day
to command
to Jesus
and proclaim
the message
of Jesus
until the day
of your time.